<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Infection Control – Infection Control</title><link>https://infection.xyzz.work/docs/infection-control/</link><description>Recent content on Infection Control</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><atom:link href="https://infection.xyzz.work/docs/infection-control/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Docs: CDC - Guidelines</title><link>https://infection.xyzz.work/docs/infection-control/cdc-guidelines/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://infection.xyzz.work/docs/infection-control/cdc-guidelines/</guid><description>
&lt;p>Infection Prevention Practices in Dental Settings&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="risks-to-dental-health-care-personnel">Risks to Dental Health Care Personnel&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Although the transfference of infectious agents is seldom in a dental setting, there still remains the potiental of both patients and dental health care personnel (DHCP) contracting a pernicious pathogen.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>During a dental procedure, both patients and (DHCP) are at a risk of being exposed to a myraid of pathogens via contact with bodily secretions such as blood, saliva, respiratory secretions, and contaminated equipment.&lt;br>
Below are some of the common diseases both patients and DHCP can contract and recommended infection prevention procedures. This will prevent transmission of pathogens while keeping patients and DHCP safe and healthy.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="bloodborne-pathogens">Bloodborne pathogens&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Bloodborne pathogens are infectious bacterium found in human blood that can potentially cause diseases in humans if exposed. These pathogens included but are not limited to hepatitis B virus (HBV), hepatitis C virus (HCV) and human immunodeficiency virus (HIV). These pathogens are transmissible in health care settings via needlesticks and other sharps-related injuries and may expose both patient and DHCP to bloodborne pathogens to lifelong chronic infections. Some of these pathogens are often carried by people unaware of their infections. Thus, it is necessary to properly follow infection prevention procedures to prevent transmission of pathogens to one another.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="how-to-protect-against-bloodborne-pathogens">How to protect against bloodborne pathogens?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>There are two tiers of precautions that are recommended by the Center of Disease and Control (CDC) to protect workers and patients. These tiers include standard precautions and transmission-based precautions. When both of precautions are applied they maximize the saftey of both DCHP and the patients.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Standard Precautions (SP)&lt;/strong> - is the primary way to prevent transmission of infectious agents. It protects both DHCP and patients not only from pathogens in human blood but other bodily fluids and secretions that one may be exposed to during provision of a procedure. Some elements of standard precautions include:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Hand hygiene.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Using personal protective equipment.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Respiratory hygiene/cough etiquette.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sharps safety, including engineering and work practice controls.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Safe injection practices.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sterilization and disinfection of instruments and devices.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Cleaning and disinfecting environmental surfaces.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Standard Precautions, applies without limitation to urine, feces, nasal secretions, sputum, vomit, and other body fluids that may be potential sources of worker exposure to infectious agents. These precautions, apply to all patients even when they are not known or suspected to be infectious. They must be used in the care of all patients, relentlessly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Transmission-Based Precautions (TBP)&lt;/strong> - is the second tier of infection prevention. It is always used in addition to standard precautions to interrupt the spread of certain pathogens. There are three categories of transmission-based precautions, these are:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Airborne: Is used for patients suspected or known to be infected with pathogens transmitted by the airborne route (e.g., tuberculosis, measles, chickenpox).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Droplet (larger than 5 microns): Is used for patients suspected or known to be infected with pathogens transmitted by respiratory droplets that are generated by a patient who is coughing, sneezinf, or talking.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Contact: Is used for patients with suspected or known infections that represent an increased risk for contact transmission.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The three different types of transmission-based precautions are applied based on what isw known or suspected about a patient&amp;rsquo;s infection. Sometimes more than one transmission category may apply.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="dental-health-care-personnel-safety">Dental Health Care Personnel Safety&lt;/h3>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>To protect the DHCP from potenitally contracting pathogens from patients, infection control programs should address immunizations of DHCP, exposure prevention and postexposure management, medical condition management and work-related illness and restrictions as well as maintan all health records in accordance with all applicable state and federal laws.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>To ensure the safety of both DHCP and patient, all DHCP must comply with the written infection control policies recommended by the CDC as facility policies. During an occurance or possibility of exposure from DHCP to patient, facilities include specific policies regarding person of contact with patients when personnel have potentially transmissible conditions.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Docs: COVID -19</title><link>https://infection.xyzz.work/docs/infection-control/covid-19/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://infection.xyzz.work/docs/infection-control/covid-19/</guid><description>
&lt;div class="alert alert-warning" role="alert">
&lt;h4 class="alert-heading">Stay at Home&lt;/h4>
The stay at home order has been continued to May 31th, 2020
&lt;/div>
&lt;h2 id="government-mandate">Government Mandate&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Governor Inslee has extended the &lt;a href="https://tribkcpq.files.wordpress.com/2020/05/four-phases.png">stay at home order&lt;/a>. There are four phases to take place throught out the months as the government re-opens. With this given information, this means that:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We are currently in &lt;code>Phase 1&lt;/code>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Stay home &amp;amp; stay healthy&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Some outdoor recreational activities&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Essential Travel&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Essential businesses open&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="what-is-coronavirus">What is Coronavirus&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Coronavirus, is any virus belonging to the family Coronaviridae. These viruses are named after the Latin word corona which characterizes the crown-like spikes on the surface of the virus. Along with the current strain causing the global pandemic, there are six other known coronaviruses that can affect humans. Each then is subdivided into four generes, the alpha, beta, gamma, and delta depending on their phylogenic clustering. These viruses include:
&lt;table class="table table-striped">
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th align="center">Name&lt;/th>
&lt;th align="center">Group&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Description&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td align="center">229E&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="center">alpha&lt;/td>
&lt;td>coronavirus&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td align="center">NL63&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="center">alpha&lt;/td>
&lt;td>coronavirus&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td align="center">OC43&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="center">beta&lt;/td>
&lt;td>coronavirus&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td align="center">HKU1&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="center">beta&lt;/td>
&lt;td>coronavirus&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td align="center">MERS-CoV&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="center">beta&lt;/td>
&lt;td>(the beta coronavirus that causes Middle East Respiratory Syndrome, or MERS)&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td align="center">SARS-CoV&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="center">beta&lt;/td>
&lt;td>(the beta coronavirus that causes severe acute respiratory syndrome, or SARS)&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td align="center">SARS-CoV-2&lt;/td>
&lt;td align="center">novel&lt;/td>
&lt;td>(the novel coronavirus that causes coronavirus disease 2019, or COVID-19)&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>People around the world commonly get infected with human coronaviruses 229E, NL63, OC43, and HKU1.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Sometimes coronaviruses that infect animals can evolve and make people sick and become a new human coronavirus. Three recent examples of this are 2019-nCoV, SARS-CoV, and MERS-CoV.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="origination-of-covid-19">Origination of COVID-19&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Coronaviruses (CoVs) originate from animals such camels, civets and bats and cause a variety of diseases in different species. In cows and pigs coronaviruses can cause enteritis, in chickens and humans they cause upper respiratory infections which can potentially be lethal to humans. SARS coronaviruses including COVID-19 are believed to have specifically originate from horseshoe bats.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The first case of (SARS-CoV-2) COVID-19 emerged in late December of 2019 after China reported cases of pneumonia in people associated with Huanan Seafood Wholesale Market in Wuhan, Hubei Province. By the end of the year, there were over 30 individuals in China with confirmed cases of the virus. Subsequently over the next few months, the virus spread to more than two dozen countries causing sickness and death to thousand of people worldwide. Currently, we are at a global pandemic with majority of the countries and islands around the world fighting against the 2019 novel coronavirus (COVID-19). Below are some of the countries affected by the coronavirus and their confirmed cases as reported by Johns Hopkins University Center for Systems Science and Engineering.&lt;/p>
&lt;img alt="pie chart image with input [italy germany united-states spain china]" id="chart-covid" src="https://charts.xyzz.work/chart?bkg=transparent&amp;amp;c=eyJkYXRhIjp7ImRhdGFzZXRzIjpbeyJkYXRhIjpbMzg3MDEzMSwzMTU1NTIyLDMxNjcwMDMxLDM0MDcyODMsMTAyMjQyXSwibGFiZWwiOiJDb25maXJtZWQgQ2FzZXMifV0sImxhYmVscyI6WyJJdGFseSIsIkdlcm1hbnkiLCJVbml0ZWQgU3RhdGVzIG9mIEFtZXJpY2EiLCJTcGFpbiIsIkNoaW5hIl19LCJvcHRpb25zIjp7ImxlZ2VuZCI6eyJsYWJlbHMiOnsiZm9udENvbG9yIjoiYmxhY2sifSwicG9zaXRpb24iOiJ0b3AifSwicGx1Z2lucyI6eyJkYXRhbGFiZWxzIjp7ImNvbG9yIjoiYmxhY2siLCJmb250Ijp7InNpemUiOiI2Iiwid2VpZ2h0Ijoibm9ybWFsIn19fSwidGl0bGUiOiIifSwidHlwZSI6InBpZSJ9&amp;amp;encoding=base64&amp;amp;h=230&amp;amp;w=500">
&lt;h2 id="signs-and-symptoms">Signs and Symptoms&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The symptoms for COVID-19 might appear as those of a cold or a flu. According to a report of World Health Organization-China Joint Mission, in 80% of known cases, COVID-19 causes mild to moderate illness. Early mild symptoms begin as a fever and a dry cough and gradually develops into moderate symptoms. Other symptoms include chills, repeated shaking with chills, muscle pain, headache, sore throat, new loss of taste and smell, severe vomitting and less frequently, diarrhea.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Although a mild case of COVID-19 fundamentally is not threatening, older population, immunocompromised, and those with underlying medical conditions such as diabetes, lung and heart diseases are at a higher risk for developing more severe perhaps even fatal complications. Severe symptoms may include shortness of breath, persistent pain or pressure in the chest, new confusion, bluish lips or face. Children have similar symptoms to adults and generally have mild illness. If any of these severe symptoms are apparent, one should consult a medical provider and seek medical attention immediately in behalf of their safety and of others they may come in contact with.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="resources">Resources&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://coronavirus.1point3acres.com/en">1Point3Acres Real Time&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/cases-updates/cases-in-us.html">CDC Cases Updates&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/types.html">CDC Human Coronavirus Types&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://coronavirus.wa.gov/">wa.gov Coronavirus Response&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.npr.org/sections/goatsandsoda/2020/01/24/798661901/wuhan-coronavirus-101-what-we-do-and-dont-know-about-a-newly-identified-disease">npr.org Coronavirus 101&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.britannica.com/science/SARS#ref779701">britannica.com SARS Pathology&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://github.com/CSSEGISandData/COVID-19">Johns Hopkins CSSE&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/symptoms-testing/symptoms.html">CDC Covid-19 Symptoms&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/symptoms-testing/symptoms.html">NPR coronavirus symptoms&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item></channel></rss>